Guide to the Isaac Hicks Papers 1791-1820 MS 297
New-York Historical Society
- Series I: Correspondence, 1791-1806; 18 Linear feet
  - Letters: 1803 Harvey, Deaves, & Harvey-Moores (Box -)
    - Letters: L, 1803 (Box 30, Folder 7)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Thomas & Amos Ladd, Paul Lanuse, and B. Lagrave. The correspondence is primarily in regard to regular business matters such as accounting, and the sale and shipment of goods. There are multiple letters in French.
      Ships Mentioned: Harmony, Sally
    - Letters: M-Ma (Except Martin, Hope & Thornely; Mather), 1803 (Box 30, Folder 8)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including David McCarthy, Machin & Macintosh, George McConnell, and Benjamin Maurice. Machin & Macintosh discuss the sale of cotton extensively. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to the shipment of goods and other regular business matters.
      Ships Mentioned: Neptune, George, Ann Maria
    - Letters: Martin, Hope & Thornely, 1803 (Box 30, Folder 9)
      This folder incudes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients: Hope & Thornely Martin. They discuss voyages that their ships have taken, the changing prices of goods, and other business matters.
      Ships Mentioned: Mercury, John
    - Letters: Mather, 1803 (Box 30, Folder 10)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client, Thomas Mather. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to accounting matters and the shipment of beef.
    - Letters: Me-My (Except Mellish; Moores), 1803 (Box 30, Folder 11)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including John Meader, Obed Mitchell, Richard Mitchell & Sons, and Morgan, Dougass, & Shaffer. The majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters such as accounting. Ann Moore requests Hicks forward a packet of letters to her brothers.
    - Letters: Mellish, 1803 (Box 30, Folder 12)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client, J & W Mellish. The correspondence is primarily in regards to accounting matters and shipment of cargo. They also ask Hicks to act as their power of attorney.
    - Letters: Moores, 1803 (Box 30, Folder 13)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client Reuben Moores. Moores discusses securing freight for ships. He also writes about the goods he is shipping, such as salt and wine.
      Ships Mentioned: Macy, Delight, Liberty, Sally
  - Letters: 1803 N-R (Rotch) (Box -)
    - Letters: N-O, 1803 (Box 31, Folder 1)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Abraham Nichols, and Joseph & George Otis. Abraham Nichols tells Hicks that he is unable to come to New York, and gives suggestions as to how to proceed with a ship entering the port. J. P. Norris requests that Hicks researchs some patents for land. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to accounting matters.
    - Letters: P (Except Paddock; Potts, 1803 (Box 31, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Paul Pease, Joseph Pitcairn, J. Pray, and L. Prudhomme. Paul Pease informs Hicks that he is pleased with how he handled a business matter. Joseph Pitcairn discusses the political climate. L. Prudhomme discusses the sale and shipment of goods. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters.
    - Letters: Paddock, 1803 (Box 31, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from Judah Paddock. Many of these letters are to Judah Paddock from other individuals about the sale and shipment of goods aboard his ship. Other letters are from Paddock to individuals other than Hicks, regarding the sale of their goods. Judah Paddock talks about the war between England and France. He also discusses shipping goods such as rice, cotton, and tobacco.
    - Letters: Potts, 1803 (Box 31, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from individuals with the surname Potts, including Dorinda Potts, John Potts, and Thomas Potts. Dorinda Potts discusses sending shells to her son John, and how Hicks can keep some for his troubles. John Potts discusses finding a place to board his daughter so that she may be educated, and then discusses sending them from Honduras to New York. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to the shipment of goods.
      Ships Mentioned: Anethusa
    - Letters: R (Except Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan; Rodman; Rotch), 1803 (Box 31, Folder 5)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Nathaniel Ray, James Rice, John Robinson, and Rocquette, Beedlemaker & Co. Nathaniel Ray discusses a voyage with a large number of passengers arriving safely. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters.
      Ships Mentioned: Orange, Commerce
    - Letters: Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan (1), 1803 (Box 31, Folder 6)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client, Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan. They discuss the evolving markets and shipping goods. They express their pleasure at the attention that has been given to their parcels. The majority of the correspondence is in regards to the sale and shipment of goods.
      Ships Mentioned: Liberty, Hiram, General Mercer
    - Letters: Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan (2), 1803 (Box 31, Folder 7)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client, Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan. They discuss shipping goods like coal, turpentine, and cotton. They also discuss how the war was not expected to be favorable for the sale of cotton, but they were wrong. A majority of the correspondence is in regard to the sale and shipment of goods, and accounting matters.
      Ships Mentioned: General Mercer, Thames, John
    - Letters: Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan (3), 1803 (Box 31, Folder 8)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client, Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan. The correspondence is primarily in regards to regular business matters.
      Ships Mentioned: Diana
    - Letters: Rodman, Samuel, 1803 (Box 31, Folder 9)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client Samuel Rodman. Rodman discusses the sale and shipment of whale products. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters.
    - Letters: Rotch, 1803 (Box 31, Folder 10)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from Thomas and William Rotch. The correspondence is predominantly in regards to regular business matters—primarily having to do with accounting. William Rotch also discusses the difficulty he is having on closing the sale on German goods.
      Ships Mentioned: Elizabeth
  - Letters: 1803 S-W (Box -)
    - Letters: S-Sm, 1803 (Box 32, Folder 1)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Joseph Adams Scott; Charles Schaffer; Peter J. Seaver; William Seger; Peter Seimson; Skinner, Fenwick & Brown; Barney Smith; and John Smith & Co. Charles Schaffer discusses how he is closing his business after the deaths of his partners. Barney Smith discusses facilitating negotiations on contracts. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters.
      Ships Mentioned: Swan, Ticklenburgh (?)
    - Letters: Spear, 1803 (Box 32, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients with the surname Spear, including Arthur Spear, QLH Spear, and Robert Spear. QLH Spear discusses the cotton trade, and how he is satisfied with the shipment of his cotton products. Robert Spear discusses American stock and raising funds, and requests additional credit for a Mr. Halliday. A large number of these letters are extremely difficult to read due to extensive bleeding of the ink.
    - Letters: St-Sy, 1803 (Box 32, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Sam Stoneman, A. Stokes, Thomas Stokes, Thomas Sturge, and Charles Sturtevant. A. Stokes and Thomas Stokes both discuss ordering cotton. Thomas Sturge quotes bible verses as he converses with Hicks. Charles Sturtevant discusses sending money.
    - Letters: T, 1803 (Box 32, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Morris Tobias & Co., George Thompson, and Benjamin Turpin. The correspondence is primarily in regards to regular business matters. George Thompson requests for Hicks to send him money and the sale and shipment of ashes. He also discusses taking custody of two children to bring them to school. Included is an excerpt of a letter from Tutein & Co. of Copenhagen, and from Thornton & Power of Hamburg. It is unknown who wrote these excerpts.
      Ships Mentioned: Sally, Arethusa
    - Letters: W, 1803 (Box 32, Folder 5)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Denny Walker, L. Wallace, John Waring, Alex Waterman, S. Waterman, and Ralph Wright & Nephew. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to accounting and other regular business matters. Also included is a Price-Current from Amsterdam. John Witchell writes to Hicks about an extensive amount of debt that Hicks owes.
      Ships Mentioned: Fortitude, Harry, Nancy
  - Letters: 1804 A-F (Box -)
    - Letters: A, 1804 (Box 33, Folder 1)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including William Abbott; Alexander, Webster, & Co.; David Alexander; and Howard Allen. William Abbott discusses the shipment of mahogany and cotton. Howard Allen writes about ship repairs. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters such as the sale and shipment of goods.
      Ships Mentioned: Milford, Warren
    - Letters: B (Except Boddington, Philips, & Sharp; Bolton), 1804 (Box 33, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including William Benson, Richard Blow, and Josiah Bradlee. Harry Barnard writes how he has decided to remain in South Africa so that there would be an American merchant to help ships from the United States when they come into port. William Benson discusses a depression in Liverpool, and how that is affecting the grain markets. He later writes that the grain market is slowly improving.
      Ships Mentioned: Fortitude, Columbia
    - Letters: Boddington, Philips, & Sharp, 1804 (Box 33, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client Boddington, Philips, & Sharp. They discuss trade embargos, accounting matters, and shipping goods like sugar and coffee. They discuss how wars in Europe have made trade difficult. Ships Mentioned: Iris
    - Letters: Bolton, Robert & John (1), 1804 (Box 33, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, Robert & John Bolton. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters. John Bolton writes of the death of Robert Bolton and how Curtis Bolton will be joining the firm under the same name.
      Ships Mentioned: Thames, Ann Maria
    - Letters: Bolton, Robert & John (2), 1804 (Box 33, Folder 5)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, Robert & John Bolton. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters. They predominantly discuss accounting and other financial issues.
      Ships Mentioned: Thames, Georgia, Angus, Washington
    - Letters: Bolton, Robert & John (3), 1804 (Box 33, Folder 6)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, Robert & John Bolton. A large amount of the correspondence is in regards to accounting matters. They also wrote to request that Hicks procure insurance for their ships. They discuss how the Sea Island cotton and rice crops had been destroyed by caterpillars and a storm.
      Ships Mentioned: Thames, Wilmont
    - Letters: C (Except Cramers, Smith & Co.; Cropper, Benson, & Co.), 1804 (Box 33, Folder 7)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including David Callaghan, Sam Coates, Alex Coffin, Ann Coffin, and James J. Coffin. Sam Coates discusses what he calls "a villainous transaction o the part of Odenheimer", and states that Odenheimer is "the most troublesome man I ever met with, and one of the most unprincipled." Ann Coffin asks Hicks to pay out dividends of their stocks. James Coffin discusses the sale of whale oil.
      Ships Mentioned: Olympus, Nancy, Hope
    - Letters: Cramers, Smith, & Co.; Cropper, Benson, & Co., 1804 (Box 33, Folder 8)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Cramers, Smith, & Co. and Cropper, Benson, & Co. Cramers, Smith, & Co discuss prices in St. Petersburg. They also discuss the purchase and sale of goods, and trade with St. Petersburg. Cropper, Benson, & Co. discuss how business has been mostly dull, with steady demands for cotton. They also discuss accounting issues and Prices Current in Liverpool.
      Ships Mentioned: Thames, Perseverance
    - Letters: D, 1804 (Box 33, Folder 9)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Davidson & Foster, The Brothers DeBauque, Thomas Dickason, and Henry Drinker. The brothers DeBauque discuss how business has been active during the time of peace. They also discuss British blockades from all ports between Ostend and Havre. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters. Some letters are in French.
      Ships Mentioned: John Morgan
    - Letters: E-F (Except Fisher, Samuel & Meirs), 1804 (Box 33, Folder 10)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including John Elkins, Charles Fawcett, and Edward Forbes. John Elkins discusses the sale and shipment of whale products, which by this time, Hicks was moving away from. Charles Fawcett discusses the sale of ashes and flaxseed. Edward Forbes writes to Hicks that his business is being taken over by Charles Fawcett
      Ships Mentioned: Venus, Susan, David, George
    - Letters: Fisher, Samuel & Meirs, 1804 (Box 33, Folder 11)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, Samuel & Meirs Fisher. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters, especially accounting.
      Ships Mentioned: Thomas
  - Letters: 1804 G-P (Box -)
    - Letters: G, 1804 (Box 34, Folder 1)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including G & A Gardner, Benjamin Garnett, and Joshua & Thomas Gilpin. The correspondence is primarily in regards to regular business matters.
      Ships Mentioned: Belvadere, Hunter, Eliza, Rainbow
    - Letters: H (Except Halliday; Harvey, Deaves, & Harvey), 1804 (Box 34, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Thomas Hazard, Levett Harris, Ralph Hare, George Hamilton, and Hopkins & Charles. Ralph Hare discusses giving an orphan boy an education. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters. Also included are letters from Isaac Hicks to Judah Paddock, where he discusses going to Albany to deal with a matter for the Merchants Bank, the state of his voyage, and business in Savannah, Georgia. Ships Mentioned: Sarah, Thames
    - Letters: Halliday, 1804 (Box 34, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from Alex Halliday. He laments that ships had not arrived when they were supposed to, and requests insurance be obtained. He later states that the insurance is no longer needed. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters.
      Ships Mentioned: Washington, Eliza, Mary
    - Letters: Harvey, Deaves, & Harvey, 1804 (Box 34, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, Harvey, Deaves, & Harvey. The correspondence is primarily in regards to regular business matters, primarily relating to the sale and shipment of goods.
      Ships Mentioned: Perseverance, Fortitude, Sally
    - Letters: J, 1804 (Box 34, Folder 5)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including John Jackson, Jonathan Jenkins, and Robert Jenkins. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters—predominantly the sale and shipment of goods and payment for goods.
    - Letters: K-L, 1804 (Box 34, Folder 6)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Peter Ketletas, Kirk & Lukens, William & John Ladd, and Thomas Lamb. A letter from Peter Ketletas discusses how a ship was destroyed in a storm. A majority of the correspondence regards accounting matters. Some letters are in French.
    - Letters: M-N, 1804 (Box 34, Folder 7)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including David McCarty; Martin, Hope, & Thornley; Thomas Mather; and Robert Moore. Martin, Hope, & Thornley discuss the sale of Georgia cotton, turpentine, and other goods. They also discuss how the market has become more favorable as the weather changed. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters, such as the sale and shipment of goods.
      Ships Mentioned: Guardian, Thames, General Mercer
    - Letters: O, 1804 (Box 34, Folder 8)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Jason Oliver, and Joseph & George Otis. The correspondence is primarily in regards to regular business matters.
    - Letters: P (Except Paddock; Potts), 1804 (Box 34, Folder 9)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Paul Pease, Silas Pipoon, Thomas Power, and John Pray. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters such as accounting. John Pray discusses a voyage that he took with his wife. H. Preble discusses how their friend Arthur (no last name) had been taken as an English prisoner and had been sent to Verdun, and how Preble plans to stay where he is until the end of the war.
    - Letters: Paddock, 1804 (Box 34, Folder 10)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from Judah Paddock. Paddock discusses his voyages to and from St. Petersburg, the cargo he is carrying, and the sale of said cargo. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to regular business matters—primarily shipping.
      Ships Mentioned: Olive, Thames
    - Letters: Potts, 1804 (Box 34, Folder 11)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients with the surname Potts, including John Potts, John Potts, and Thomas Potts. John Potts discusses shipping mahogany and other goods, and requests insurance to be procured. He asks Hicks to help secure an education for a boy and two girls, just as Hicks had for Potts children.
      Ships Mentioned: Columbus, John, Lady Carlton
  - Letters: 1804 Q-Z (Box -)
    - Letters: Q, 1804 (Box 35, Folder 1)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Quenouille, Lanchon, Harin, Spear & Co. The correspondence is primarily in regard to regular business matters.
    - Letters: R (Except Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan), 1804 (Box 35, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Robert Roberts, John Robinson & Sons, R. Beedlemaker & Co., Samuel Rodman, and Thomas Rotch. One letter from John Robinson & Sons thanks Hicks for suggesting a new firm to do business with. Samuel Rodman discusses difficulty with imports as his harbor is iced over. Thomas Rotch discusses his dismay at the fall in value of Merchants' Bank stock. Some letters are in French.
    - Letters: Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan (1), 1804 (Box 35, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client, Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan. They write about how Hicks has quit the commissions business, and how he "now merely purpose making a few shipments occasionally." They write about insurance coverage, the shipment of goods, and accounting matters. One printed letter discusses the stagnation of the grain market.
      Ships Mentioned: Charlestown, John, Thames
    - Letters: Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan (2), 1804 (Box 35, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client, Rathbone, Hughes, & Duncan. They write about how the General Mercer arrived in a damaged state. They discuss the sale of cotton and other goods, prices current, and other regular business matters.
      Ships Mentioned: General Mercer, George Barclay
    - Letters: S, 1804 (Box 35, Folder 5)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including John Searing, William Seger, Elias Shockley, Arthur Spear, and Robert Spear. The correspondence is predominantly in regards to regular business matters.
      Ships Mentioned: Ambition
    - Letters: T, 1804 (Box 35, Folder 6)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Tayleur & Park, Thornton & Power, and George Thompson. Thornton & Power discuss a blockade of the Elbe River, and how it has had an effect on goods such as coffee and sugar. George Thompson discusses how Captain Wallace had no legal pretense for detaining Thompson's goods in Charleston. He also asks Hicks to explain some strange letters.
      Ships Mentioned: John, Milford, Arthur, Nancy
    - Letters: U-Z, 1804 (Box 35, Folder 7)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including David Wallace, Samuel Walker, Frances Welman, Mary White, and P & D Urquhard. The correspondence is primarily in regards to regular business matters.
      Ships Mentioned: Rose in Bloom, Arthusa
  - Letters: 1805 A-P (Box -)
    - Letters: A-B (Except Bolton), 1805 (Box 36, Folder 1)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including Roger Benson; and Baddington, Philip, Sharp, & Co. Roger Benson requests information regarding selling woolen products. He later laments that his goods have been sold for lower prices than he would have liked. Baddington, Philip, Sharp & Co. discuss a hurricane that ravaged some ships. Some letters are in French.
    - Letters: Bolton, Robert & John, 1805 (Box 36, Folder 2)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients Robert & John Bolton. They discuss the sale of goods such as whale oil, and pot ashes; stating that they hope they sell well but there could be extenuating circumstances. They write about the great scarcity of money and request a small loan from Hicks. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to accounting matters.
    - Letters: C (Except Cramers, Smith & Co.), 1805 (Box 36, Folder 3)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his clients, including David McCarty, Carter & Roane, Alex Coffin, James Coffin, and Ann Coffin. David McCarty requests patience from Hicks regarding payment of bills, because he had been having legal issues that he needed to deal with. Stephen Cathalan, Jr. discusses the death of his father and how he will be taking over the business. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to accounting matters.
    - Letters: Cramers, Smith & Co., 1805 (Box 36, Folder 4)
      This folder includes correspondence to Isaac Hicks from his client Cramers, Smith, & Co. A majority of the correspondence is in regards to the sale and shipment of goods between St. Petersburg, Russia and New York.
    - Letters: D-G, 1805 (Box 36, Folder 5)